<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The assenters sayings published in their own words for the information of the people : being in requital of Roger L'Estrange's Dissenters sayings / by an indifferent hand.</title>
            <author>Indifferent hand.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4019</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12499670</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12499670</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 303:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The assenters sayings published in their own words for the information of the people : being in requital of Roger L'Estrange's Dissenters sayings / by an indifferent hand.</title>
                  <author>Indifferent hand.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>L'Estrange, Roger, --  Sir, 1616-1704. --  Dissenters sayings.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Aſſenters Sayings, PUBLISHED <hi>In their own Words.</hi> For the Information of the PEOPLE: Being in Requital of <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange's</hi> DISSENTERS SAYINGS.</p>
            <p>By an Indifferent Hand.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Henry Jones. 1681.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62653:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>In this Collection you will find <hi>Sayings</hi> of two ſorts, ſome Good, and ſome Bad; the Good are all ſpoken in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor of <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> by men of as much Piety and Learning, as any have been in the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. Among the Bad ones, you will find ſome Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick and Blaſphemous, ſome in favor of Debauchery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In making this Collection, I have taken care to avoid that which <hi>L'Eſtrange</hi> is ſo frequently guilty of in his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Diſſenters Sayings,</hi> viz. taking a line in one place, two or three words in another, and a word from another, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them head and ſhoulders into one Sentence; which thus jumbled together, ſpeak quite contrary to the Author's ſenſe and meaning: So that to ſay the truth, ſome of thoſe <hi>Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> are not the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> but <hi>L'Eſtrange's.</hi> Now here you will find the whole Sentence laid down in the words of the Author, without the leaſt alteration. I ſhall conclude with my hearty Prayer to God, That <hi>Aſſenter,</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter,</hi> and all other Names of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> and Cauſes of Animoſity may be taken away from among us for ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62653:3"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THE Deſign of the enſuing Collection, is, in ſome meaſure, to put a Check to thoſe Clamorous Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries that are daily ſent forth againſt the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,</hi> eſpecially in thoſe two famed Pamphlets, called, <hi>The Diſſenters Sayings,</hi> &amp;c. And to inform the World, That the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are no ſuch manner of Perſons, as <hi>R. L. Heraclitus</hi> Club, and the late fam'd <hi>William Gould,</hi> cum multis aliis, would repreſent them to the Common People for; and there is nothing more plain, than that many <hi>ſober Aſſenters</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from them: For you ſhall find many of theſe <hi>Sayings</hi> ſpoken in favor of the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> by Men of more Brains and Learning, and therefore more capable of judging, than <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange,</hi> and though (being Guide to the inferiour Clergy, as the Worſhipful <hi>JEST-Aſs</hi> was pleas'd to ſtile himſelf in a Letter to a young Divine at <hi>CAMBRIDGE</hi>) he may with Authority correct them, yet certainly he will not do ſo by thoſe of the ſuperior Clergy. Men, of far more Holineſs and Piety, whoſe <hi>Sayings</hi> are more to be regarded, than the envious and malicious <hi>Railings</hi> of every proſligate <hi>Buffoon:</hi> Men of far better Eſtates, and larger Revenues, whereby they are not ſo liable to be impoſed upon by a debauch'd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, or an imperious Strumpet; a preſſing Poverty, or an inſatiable Revenge; a covetous Bookſeller, or a turbulent Clergy-man; the one promiſing to pay well for his Copy, and the other to make larger Contributions among thoſe of his Tribe: For it is apparent to all unprejudic'd Perſons, that the whole deſign and ultimate end of all his Writings, is, to promote the <hi>Roman Intereſt,</hi> ſupply his Neceſſity, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate his Revenge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62653:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Aſſenters Sayings.</hi> PUBLISHED In their own WORDS TO Inform the PEOPLE.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>I ſhall Introduce the <hi>Reader</hi> with a <hi>Choice Collection</hi> of the <hi>Sayings</hi> of a Great Champion of the<hi>Aſſenters:</hi> wherein he endeavours to prove <hi>K. C.</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> to be the Third Perſon in the <hi>Trinity.</hi> 2ly, That there is no Salvation to be obtained out of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. THE firſt Objection is, ſay they, <hi>What doth your Scripture Proofs make for</hi> King Charles? <hi>I anſwer,</hi> With thoſe that hate Him and the Truth, the <hi>Proofs</hi> are of little or no force: With ſuch as love Him and the Truth, the <hi>Proofs</hi> will prevail. There are darker <hi>Proofs</hi> than theſe brought to prove the verity of our Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt. Eccho to the Voice from Heaven,</hi> Printed 1652. in the <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As the <hi>Jews</hi> will find Objections enough againſt the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> ſo many will find Objections againſt this <hi>King;</hi> but let them take heed what they ſay againſt Him, for Jeſus knew that the Scriptures heretofore was dark, and therefore he ſaid to them that ſpake againſt his own Perſon then, <hi>It was forgiven them:</hi> but ſaith he, <hi>Whoſoever ſpeaketh a word againſt the Holy Ghoſt, it ſhall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62653:4"/>never be forgiven him,</hi> Matth. 12.32. That is, <hi>againſt his appearance in this King,</hi> John 14.26. Jer. 9.28. which thing is ſo clear, that all the Myſteries of God are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by it: So that now an Angel ſwears that time ſhall be no more for Ignorance to ſhelter under, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. For this <hi>King</hi> is that <hi>Key of David,</hi> by which all Secrets was locked up, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7. and by which <hi>Key</hi> all now is opened, for this Day of Light was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be in a <hi>King,</hi> and therefore it is ſaid in <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.7. he limiteth a day, ſaying in <hi>David, To day,</hi> after ſo long time, giving to underſtand, that the <hi>Day</hi> was not the Apoſtles <hi>Time,</hi> nor <hi>David</hi>'s time, but our time. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſt ſignifies <hi>Anointed</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and I hope none will deny the King to be <hi>the Lords Anointed;</hi> the Lord, our Lord, is the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> is the <hi>Lord's Anointed,</hi> or in <hi>Greek,</hi> his <hi>Christ;</hi> for all knows, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a Greek word; and one of the moſt learned Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> upon the hearing of my Book read before him, gave this ſentence of Approbation upon it, That he wiſhed that all Men were of my mind; and for the <hi>Third Perſon,</hi> all the true Miniſters in the King's Dominions fifteen years ago gave him the place of the <hi>Third Perſon,</hi> ſaying of him to God the Father in their Prayers, <hi>CHARLES, by thy Grace and Providence, King of great</hi> Britain, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>Defender of the true Ancient Catholick and Apoſtolick Faith, next under Thee and thy Son, ſupream Head and Governour.</hi> Ibid.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Here they place the <hi>King</hi> to be next to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> making no mention of the <hi>Floly Ghoſt,</hi> except they meant Him to be the King. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62653:4"/>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is the Chief Governour of the <hi>Saints on Earth,</hi> by the Apoſtles Teſtimony, for when the <hi>Decree</hi> is ſent to the People of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28. it runs thus; <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt, and to us, to lay upon you no other burdens than theſe:</hi> And for the Miniſters words, by the orational ſenſe of them, we muſt underſtand them thus, That by the <hi>King,</hi> they mean the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> and <hi>third Perſon;</hi> or elſe, we muſt underſtand thus, That they do not acknowledge the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> to be the <hi>third Perſon,</hi> for they ſpake of <hi>God the Father,</hi> and of <hi>God the Son,</hi> and <hi>King Charles</hi> to be next and immediate under the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son.</hi> Ibid.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Here they put out the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> from being the <hi>third Perſon,</hi> except they mean him to be ſignified to us in the <hi>King's Perſon;</hi> which may very well be, for <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> in the firſt place, where he ſpeaks of <hi>God's ſending the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter:</hi> and by this <hi>Comforter,</hi> we muſt underſtand him according to the Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.16. that is, another <hi>Comforter</hi> like unto me, not only a <hi>Spirit,</hi> but a <hi>perfect Man.</hi> Ibid.</p>
            <p n="8">8. We muſt underſtand the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> to be a <hi>man,</hi> for they that are ſent to us in the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are <hi>Men,</hi> yet he that is thus dignified is but <hi>one man.</hi> Ibid.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Chriſt ſaith, ſpeaking of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. <hi>He ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf, but what he heareth that ſhall he ſpeak.</hi> Ibid.</p>
            <p n="10">10. From whence you may underſtand, That the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> though called here a <hi>Spirit,</hi> as elſewhere, is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62653:5"/>not a <hi>Spirit</hi> only, but a <hi>Man</hi> alſo; for he is a <hi>Hearer</hi> and a <hi>Receiver</hi> of the <hi>things of Chriſt,</hi> and his Errand is not to ſpeak of himſelf, or to ſet forth himſelf, but to glorifie <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which thing you know, <hi>King Charles</hi> did above all that ever was. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. You ſay, The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> came upon the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and ſo the promiſe of <hi>Chriſt, Joh.</hi> 14. was fulfilled, and there is no further manifeſtation of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> to be expected amongſt men: I ſay no; for the great manifeſtation of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> was reſerved untill the time of the Reſtoration of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and thus you ſee, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> being amongſt them, bids them wait for the promiſe of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> and not depart out of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> untill it came upon them; they thinking there ſhould be a full manifeſtation of it in their days, <hi>ſaid, Lord wilt thou at this time reſtore the Kingdom to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> for then they underſtood the fulneſs of the promiſe ſhould be, but the Lord puts by their queſtion, ſaith to them, they ſhould receive a competent meaſure of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> fit for their work, which was but the influence or beams of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſo called the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> as we ſay of the Sun when it ſhineth upon a Houſe, there is the Sun, though indeed it is but the Sun beams; and the Sun hath its diſtinct body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, though no man is able to diſern the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of its beams; and as <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Kings and Prophets, ſaw <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> yet they ſaw not his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, with their eyes, as the Apoſtles did; ſo the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſaw the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> yet they ſaw not his Body with their Bodily eyes, as we ſaw. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of two, one he calls the firſt born, and that is <hi>Jeſus, Heb.</hi> 1.6. who firſt was Typed out in the Sacrifices, who cometh and Sacrificed himſelf;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62653:5"/>the ſecond he calls <hi>He,</hi> ſaying, <hi>When He cometh into the World, Heb.</hi> 10.5. That is the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which is ready to be a body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to do his Will, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. In the firſt Diſpenſation under the Law, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> was amongſt them, and ſpake by their Prophets, whoſe Form of Speech is, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> and that it is the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> that uttered himſelf by them, ſo in the ſecond Diſpenſation under the Goſpell, you ſhall find the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> comes in the beginning in S. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> and ſo forward to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, increaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it, and that the Prophets under the Goſpel uſe this Form of Speech, <hi>Thus ſaith the Holy Ghoſt. Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. As the appearance of <hi>Jeſus</hi> was to end the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie and Prophets under the Law, ſo the appearance of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in <hi>Charles,</hi> is to conſummate all Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Prophets for ever, that now no more Prophets are to be expected: for the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> hath ſealed with his bloud that true way by which all the World is to worſhip God, and that ſhall Unite all in Love, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles. Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. The <hi>Jews</hi> ſay the ſame thing that there are two <hi>Meſſiahs,</hi> one they call <hi>Meſsiah</hi> the Son of <hi>David,</hi> the other <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> which <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> as they affirm, was to die in the laſt War of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and afterwards to riſe again, and ſhew him to be <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of <hi>David;</hi> and that <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſhall ſit in the Throne of <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of <hi>David,</hi> and Rule for ever all that he hath, and be his <hi>Viceroy,</hi> as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was to <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> which Aſſertion in this point is more conſonant to the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, then any holds it forth amongſt our Divines; yet I ſay the Spirit of Infallibility is in our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62653:6"/>Church, by which they, guided according to the great Providence of God, to give the King the great Honour due unto him; though many of them did not conſider what they ſaid, and now will not own it in the true ſence: but of this I am ſure, that the Biſhops who firſt ſaid it, were men of underſtanding, and did nothing ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſome of them Propheſied when the King came from <hi>Spain,</hi> that he ſhould die to maintain the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. If Blaſphemy be in me, then <hi>Chriſt</hi> Blaſphemes, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Blaſphemes, the <hi>Church</hi> Blaſphemes, the <hi>Jews</hi> Blaſphemes, for we are of one Aſſertion. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not proud, be not ye fooliſhly proud for him; for you ſhall have but a ſmall reward for it, for <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth permit his Servant to be equal with him, and I dare ſay, if he had met in his day with ſuch a faithfull King, as King <hi>Charles,</hi> the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> would have put him before him; but the humility of King <hi>Charles</hi> would have been ſuch that he would have been glad to follow on his knees the laſt of all his Diſciples, being over-joy'd to have that Honour to ſee his Preſence and Perſon upon Earth. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. Who is he that doth prefer King <hi>Charles</hi> to the place that <hi>Jeſus</hi> would give unto the meaneſt of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants that is to be equal with him; for my part I do not, and I know no Servant of his will take it upon him, and I know King <hi>Charles</hi> muſt rather be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to it, for <hi>Chriſt</hi> will give it him by force, and he muſt receive it, or anger his <hi>Lord,</hi> which I know he will not do. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. For ſo indeed I am ſent before King <hi>Charles,</hi> to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62653:6"/>prepare a People to receive him; as S. <hi>John</hi> of Old was ſent to prepare the way of the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> the caſe is the ſame. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. I ſuppoſe ſuch an account is expected from me, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> gave the People, that is, a Narration of my calling to this work, wherein you ſhall find God's ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial purpoſe in me, preparing me from my Infancy, and alſo leading me by His Special Hand, from time to time, and declaring his minde unto me, giving me to underſtand wherefore I had my being, ſhewing ſpecial ſigns upon me, while I was yet an Infant, to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of my Parents, and of all my friends and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that they were forced to Propheſie, and to ſay that God had appointed me for ſome great Work. <hi>ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. Lifting up mine Eyes from my work, I beheld the Angel of the Lord all in white ſtood upon the Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, with a flaming Sword in his hand ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy me. <hi>Eccho to the Voice from Heaven,</hi> pag. 20.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Comparing this trouble of mine by Kindred, to that of my <hi>Saviour</hi>'s, who was in a like manner dealt with by his own Kindred, I taking it to be unto me a ſimilitude of my Saviours grave, I reſted confidently, that I ſhould be delivered the third day, the firſt and ſecond day came and I had nothing, when I did ask for ſomething, but threatning words; and by that the third was come, I was very faint; and as I lay upon my Bed the third day in the morning, expecting ſome ſign of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from God, there came in at the Window a round Cloud, in Colour like unto the Rain Bow, and it covered me, abiding upon me about a quarter of an hour, and when it came upon me, I was ſo revived, as if I had eaten all the Delicacies in the World; and after a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62653:7"/>quarter of an hour, the Cloud departed out of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow in the ſame manner as it came in, untill it aſcended out of my ſight. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 33.</p>
            <p n="23">23. He anſwered, You ſaid, <hi>Woe be to them that are not of this Houſe ſhortly,</hi> meaning the Queens Chappel. I ſaid, Friend, you err as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, for I did not mean the Chappel, but this Houſe of my Body, and of my Faith and Judgment. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 43.</p>
            <p n="24">24. I ſaid, I believe we ſhall be better acquainted, for you are the King's Secretary, and I am God's Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. To Secretary <hi>Windebank, ibid. pag.</hi> 45.</p>
            <p n="25">25. <hi>William Heyfer</hi> reading a Book, called the Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizing of the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book, which I diſputed againſt, but not being able longer to heare him read ſuch Blaſphemies again the truth, I cried out, ſaying, <hi>Lord for thy truths ſake, ſhew thy diſpleaſure againſt this wicked Book,</hi> and as I ſpake, a mighty flaſh of fire ſtruck againſt the window, put all in a fright, and the fellow caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Book. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 51.</p>
            <p n="26">26. I had the ſame Spirit to declare the Scripture as did Pen them. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 54.</p>
            <p n="27">27. When <hi>Green</hi> the Recorder asked me what I was? ſuppoſe I had anſwered him; ſaying, <hi>I am the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt have no other God but me;</hi> I am ſure I had not ſinned in it. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 67.</p>
            <p n="28">28. As I was deſiring God to ſhew me a figure of the Judgment to come, and the Glory that is to follow, I fell into a Trance, that I ſeemed to be at <hi>Mayſellan-kad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ruſe,</hi> where I was brought up, and I was with my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62653:7"/>elder Brother by the River-ſide, it was a glorious Day, about Two in the Afternoon, but on a ſudden my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was gone I knew not how nor where, and as I lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up mine eyes again, the Sun by degrees became dark, ſo that the Stars appeared about it; at which darkneſs the Sheep did cry and run to ſeek a ſhelter in holes of the Rocks, as they uſe to do in thoſe parts, when a darkneſs comes before a ſtorm; and all the light of Heaven was taken away. Then appeared by a mad-man's houſe that lived there when I was a Boy, a great Bonfire, and people making merry about it: but as I ſtill waited for ſome light above, I eſpied a little white Cloud breaking out in the North-eaſt, after which the Sky appeared, and upon the Sky appeared the <hi>King's Arms</hi> as it is upon blue in ſome Churches, and it rid upon the Heavens very terrible towards South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt; and as the light appeared, abundance of waters ſprung out of a dry Hill Northwards. <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 107, 108.</p>
            <p n="29">29. The interpretation of it is thus, My Brother did ſignifie <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> appearing, and after abſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for a time from his people. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">30. I beheld and ſaw a peaceable modeſt young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſtanding on a Plain, &amp; another of a malicious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and looked enviouſly upon the modeſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and ſhe took up a ſmall Pipe as it were of green Glaſs, but I was given to underſtand it was the ſting of a Serpent, and ſhe did put it in her mouth and blew it againſt the modeſt woman; and they came cloſe together, and did blow one againſt the other ſo furiouſly, that a Wheel of ſire in colour like the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow covered them both, that I thought ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the modeſt woman: but at laſt ſhe that took up the ſting was conſumed to nothing, and the modeſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62653:8"/>woman remained peaceably, and did ſhine with beauty far more glorious than before. The firſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſignifies <hi>the Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the other, <hi>the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> that took up the <hi>Sting</hi> againſt <hi>the Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but at laſt <hi>the Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> gets the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and the other is conſumed. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 113.</p>
            <p n="31">31. On <hi>Good Fryday</hi> at Night about Ten a Clock, as I came from one Mr. <hi>John Lee,</hi> who lived then in <hi>Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-houſe Lane,</hi> and I lived in <hi>Cob's Yard,</hi> but as I came by <hi>Black-Fryars Church</hi> along the Paved Alley, it being a light Night, over againſt the Church-yard, there I met a man all in black, with a black long Cloak, like a Presbyterian Miniſter, and we juſtled cloſe, he fell before me, as if a black Cloak had been ſpread upon the ground, and vaniſhed away. This was that <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian evil Spirit,</hi> which knew I ſhould diſcover his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and baniſh him out of the World, as I did in part in 1646.</p>
            <p n="32">32. I ſay, there is no true Church of God in all the world, but <hi>the Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth there is no Salvation for Souls but in it: there is no Elect viſibly ſeen, ſave thoſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and all the Elect muſt come to Unity with theſe in Form of Worſhip, Doctrine and Diſcipline, before they can be juſtified and ſaved. <hi>England</hi> at this time contains all the Elect of God, and thoſe that will not come to this Church, muſt be deſtroyed. <hi>Preface to the Eccho to the Voice from Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">33. The Reformation of <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> of the <hi>Calviniſts, Hugonites</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>John Knox</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are but rebellious Rules, like the Rods of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers</hi> in <hi>Egypt. Voice from Heaven,</hi> p. 54.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62653:8"/>
            <p n="34">34. The Book of <hi>Common Prayer</hi> is promiſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8, 9, 10. and is called <hi>the way of Holineſs,</hi> wherein a way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring man, though a Fool, ſhall not err therein. <hi>Ibid. page</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>So much for this <hi>Welch Prophet</hi> and mighty <hi>Gigantick Champion</hi> of the <hi>Prelacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35. There ſprang up a mighty Bramble on the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Lake <hi>Lemane,</hi> that ſpread and flouriſhed with ſuch a ſudden growth, that by the induſtry of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents abroad, and partly by its own indefatigable pains and pragmaticalneſs, it quite over-ran the whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. <hi>Parker's Defence Policy.</hi> p. 663.</p>
            <p n="36">36. It is abſolutely neceſſary to the Peace and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World, that the Supream Magiſtrate of every Commonwealth ſhould be veſted with a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to govern and conduct the Conſciences of Subjects in matters of Religion. Dr. <hi>Parker.</hi> p. 10.</p>
            <p n="37">37. Unleſs Princes have power to bind their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to that Religion that they apprehend moſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to publick peace and tranquillity, and reſtrain thoſe religious miſtakes that tends to its ſubverſion, they are no better than Statues and Images of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. <hi>page</hi> 13.</p>
            <p n="38">38. A Prince is endued with a Power to Conduct Religion, and that muſt be ſubject to his Dominion as well as other things. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p n="39">39. If Princes ſhould forgoe their Soveraignty over men's Conſciences in matters of Religion, they leave themſelves leſs power than is abſolutely neceſſary. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62653:9"/>
            <p n="40">40. The Supream Government of every Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, where ever it is lodged, muſt of neceſſity be univerſal, abſolute, and uncontrollable in all affairs whatſoever, that concern the Intereſts of Mankind, and the ends of Government. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="41">41. He in whom the Supream Power reſides, having Authority to aſſign to every Subject his proper Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and amongſt others, thoſe of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> the exerciſe whereof as he has power to transfer upon others, ſo he may, if he pleaſe, reſerve it to himſelf. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere, </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether this be not a learned expoſition of <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. And whether there were any Kings in that Commiſſion?</p>
            <p n="42">42. The Government of Religion was veſted in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by an antecedent Right to Chriſt. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p n="43">43. Men may think of things according to their own perſwaſions, and aſſert the freedom of their Judgments againſt all the powers of the Earth. This is the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the mind of Man within its own Dominions, its Kingdom is intellectual; whilſt Conſcience acts within its proper ſphere, the Civil Power is ſo far from doing it violence, that it never can. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 89.</p>
            <p n="44">44. Mankind hath the ſame natural right to liberty of Conſcience in matters of religious Worſhip, as in Affairs of Juſtice and Honeſty; that is to ſay, a liberty of judgment, but not of practice. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 92.</p>
            <p n="45">45. In Caſes and Diſputes of publick Concernment, private men are not properly <hi>ſui juris,</hi> they have no power over their own actions; they are not to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62653:9"/>by their own judgments, or determined by their own wills, but by the commands and determinations; of the publick Conſcience: and if there be any ſin in the Command, he that impoſed it ſhall anſwer for it, and not I, whoſe duty it is to obey. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 308.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere, </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether according to this Poſition; a Man or his Horſe be the happieſt Creature?</p>
            <p n="46">46. The Commands of Authority will warrant my Obedience, my Obedience will hallow, or at leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my Actions, and ſo ſecure me from ſin, if not from errour. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="47">47. In all doubtful and diſputable caſes, it's better to err with Authority, than to be in the right againſt it. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere, </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether this be not an excellent Expoſition upon <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. we ought <hi>to obey God rather than man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="48">48. God hath appointed Magiſtrates to be his Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees and Officials, to act and determine in moral Vertues and pious Devotions according to all Accidents and Emergencies of Affairs: to aſſign new particulars of the Divine Law, to declare new bounds of right and wrong, which the Law of God neither doth nor can Limit. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 80.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quere,</hi> Whether this be not proved out of <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.17, 18, 19, 20. Neither ſhall he multiply Wives to himſelf, that his Heart turn not away: Neither ſhall he greatly multiply to himſelf Silver or Gold.</p>
            <p>And it ſhall be when he ſitteth upon the Throne of his Kingdom, that he ſhall write him a Copy of this Law in a Book out of that which is before the Prieſt the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall Read therein
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62653:10"/>all the Days of his Life, that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, to keep all the words of this Law, and theſe Statutes to do them.</p>
            <p>That his Heart be not lifted up above his Brethren, and that he turn not aſide there from, to the right Hand or the Left.</p>
            <p n="49">49. Moral Virtues being the moſt Material and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full part of all Religion, is alſo the utmoſt end of all its Duties, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 69.</p>
            <p n="50">50. All Religion muſt of neceſſity be reſolved into <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> or Morality, the former is meer Impoſture; and therefore all that is true muſt be Reduced to the latter, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 76.</p>
            <p n="51">51. It's abſolutely neceſſary to the Peace and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Kingdoms, that there be ſet up a more ſevere Government over mens Conſciences, and Religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, then over their Vices and Immoralities. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Eccleſiaſtical Policy. <hi>p.</hi> 53.</p>
            <p n="52">52. Princes may with leſs Hazard give Liberty to Mens Vices and Debaucheries, then their Conſciences. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 55.</p>
            <p n="53">53. If Princes will be Reſolute they may make the moſt ſtubborn Conſcience bend to their Reſolutions, <hi>Parker. p.</hi> 271.</p>
            <p n="54">54. Princes muſt be ſure to bind on at firſt their Eccleſiaſtical Laws with the ſtraiteſt Knot, and after ward force them in by the ſeverity of their Execution. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 121.</p>
            <p n="55">55. It's ſo eaſy for men to Deſerve being puniſhed for their Conſciences, that there is no Nation in the World, in which, were Government rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and duly Managed, miſtakes and abuſes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, would not ſupply the Gallies with vaſtly great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Numbers then villany. <hi>Ibid.</hi> 223.</p>
            <p n="66">66. There is not any ſort of People ſo inclinable to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62653:10"/>Seditious Practices, as the Trading part of a Nation <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 49.</p>
            <p n="57">57. Of all Villains the well meaning, Zealot is the moſt Dangerous. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 154.</p>
            <p n="58">58. Princes cannot pluck a pin out of the Church, but immediately the State ſhakes and totters, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 166.</p>
            <p n="59">59. No Rites nor Ceremonies can be eſteemed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in the worſhip of God, unleſs they tend to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch men either in their Practices, or their Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Deity. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 82.</p>
            <p n="60">60. 'Tis no part of the Princes concernment to inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Rules of moral good or evil, that is the care and the prerogative, of a Superiour Law-Giver <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 241.</p>
            <p n="61">61. Chriſt was not only in an hot Fict of Zeal but in a ſeeming Fury and Tranſport of paſſion. <hi>Preface. p.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p n="62">62. I do profeſs to all the World, that the Transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Indifferent Opinions into neceſſary Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith, hath been that <hi>Inſana Laurus,</hi> or curſed Bay Tree, the cauſe of all our brawling and contention. Biſhop <hi>Bramhall. p.</hi> 141.</p>
            <p n="63">63. When the Civil Magiſtrate takes upon him to Determine any particular Forms of outward worſhip, it is of no worſe conſequence, then if he ſhould go about to Define the ſignification of all the words uſed in the worſhip of God. <hi>Parker. p.</hi> 110.</p>
            <p n="64">64. Some have thought they could not be eſteemed Loyal, if they appeared Devout: And therefore to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the one Character, were willing not only to throw off, but openly to reproach the other all they could, Mr. <hi>Burnets</hi> Sermon before the Court of Aldermen. <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1680/1. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p n="65">65. It is not to be conceived, that amongſt them who
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62653:11"/>are ſo Zealous in the oppoſing of a Plot againſt his Majeſties Perſon, our holy Religion, and the peace and ſafety of the Nation; there can be any that dares mock God and man ſo audaciouſly as to be deſigning any ſuch thing themſelves, the ſame time they are accuſing others of it. To ſuppoſe it otherwiſe, were to give Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to the falſe ſuggeſtion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and baſe contrivances of thoſe who Deſign nothing more than to take us off from watching over their Motions, by engaging us one againſt another, and infuſing ſuch Jealouſies, as may effectually divide us among our ſelves: The only way that is now left without a Forraign power, firſt to break, and then to Conquer thoſe in ſeperated parties, whoſe united ſtrength they know they cannot Reſiſt. <hi>Ibid. p</hi> 18.</p>
            <p n="66">66. God be Thanked none of our Differences are ſuch as we may Deſpair of Reconciling them, or at leaſt of bearing with one anothers Infirmities and Miſtakes, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p n="67">67. Many that are for the Church ſhould abate of their ſtiffneſs, in things not Eſſential; and unite at home all that are capable of it by adjuſting matters among our ſelves and thoſe cannot come into that Union be at leaſt Inoffenſive to them that do. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p n="68">68. The Kings great ſtrength is his peoples love. Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Remedy of the Diſtempers of the times. <hi>p.</hi> 285.</p>
            <p n="69">69. But theſe, like the grave, ſwallow all, the good, the bad, life, Liberty, and Eſtate; Families, poſterity, Root and Branch, in one Day, I mean ſuch as are Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panners or Countenancers of them; ſham-Evidence, falſe Witneſſes, whoſe Tongue can Swear and unſwear, whoſe Tongue perhaps have Cut the Throats of many a poor Innocent already, and ſtill want more work, more work; men of no Honour, no Honeſty, no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, (except of that Notorious and Bloody Religion, that is worſe then no Religion) you may have more
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62653:11"/>Truth, more kindneſs more Fidelity, fairer quarter from Infidels, then from ſuch Bigotted-Catholicks, that think it is Religion and pleaſing to God to cut men's Throats. Horrid Sin of Man-Catching, <hi>p.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="60">60. Which they dare not always do in the down right <hi>Godfrey</hi>-way of Murdering; (that has and may) prove Dangerous, no the Devil is crafty, and his Agents and Emiſſaries can improve in Wit as well as Malice; they do the Feat, lay their Snares, catch men (not in the night and be Hang'd) but at noon Day and by Law; not with Cruel Hands, but a way worth two on't) with Venemous Tongues of a Serpent. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="61">61. And that by falſe Oaths, falſe Tongues ſwearing <hi>pro &amp; con;</hi> as if thoſe that will ſwear you Twenty Oaths in an hour, for God have Mercy, will ſcruple at an Oath for Money, and to have all other Oaths and Sins pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, into the Bargain <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p n="62">62. Wicked men by falſe Oaths can do the Buſineſs, do their own Buſineſs, get Rewards for catching Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent men, and not always (though ſometimes) the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows alſo for their pains, in ſetting Snares to catch men, theſe are the men that can do any mans buſineſs how Innocent ſoever, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="63">63. Holy <hi>David</hi> compares theſe lurking Catch-poles, theſe Knights of the Poſt (that wait in all Companies and ſpie in all Aſſemblies) unto a Lion Lurking in his Den; or in ſecret places, lying in wait privily and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome Covert (perhaps of the Righteous Law) to catch men, to catch their Prey. Where men walk, where men Talk, by the way-ſide ſays <hi>David,</hi> they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate into all Companies, all buſineſs, all Aſſemblies,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62653:12"/>where they can get Admittance, they are never out of their way; they catch at the words of a Miniſter in the Pulpit, of a Judg upon the Bench, laying Snares for him that Reproveth in the Gate, Trepanning their very Comrades, their Friends and Familiars, like <hi>Jeremies</hi> Companions, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.10. Saying, Peradventure he will be inticed, and we ſhall prevail againſt him, and we ſhall take our Revenge on him. But this they do with all privacy imaginable, perhaps under an Oath of Secrecy, to pump the deeper, under Colour of Friendſhip, or under Colour of ſome doubtfull word that will bear two Sences, and they ſhall always take it in the worſt Sence and in the wrong Sence, and inconſiſtent in Sence, and incoherant with all former or ſubſequent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or make Additions, villanous Additions of their own, theſe are the Dark-Lanthorn men, that like. <hi>Faux,</hi> walk with a Vizard on, the vizard of Honeſty, of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Friendſhip, or perhaps of good Fellowſhip, laying their Snares ſecretly and in the Dark, to catch Men. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p n="64">64. Theſe are the Blades of our times, and the men of Valour, that dare ſtrut like thoſe Giants of old, that bid Heaven battle, and did Defiance to the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Blaſpheme him to his Face, and if ever they Pray to him, 'tis only in jeer, as when they pray to God to Damn them, Damn them. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="65">65. Words are loſt, and much more holy Scripture words are loſt on theſe ſtout Hectors, Atheiſts, falſe Witneſſes, men-catchers, Catch-poles, and Sham-Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences. God bleſs us all from them, and grant we may never come into their Clutch, or within the reach and probability of their Oaths, their Oaths, the Snares where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they catch men, many honeſt men, uſeful men;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62653:12"/>nay, therefore theſe men-catchers lay their Snares and their oathing-gins to catch them; becauſe they are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and uſefull, and ſtand juſt in the way to hinder their Villanous Plots and Deſign. Well go on, and ſwear and Dam your ſelves to the Pit of Hell, and let men perſwade you there's no ſuch thing as Hell, at worſt but a kind of Purgatory, (a certain refining crucible only to take away your Droſs) and for a little money, or killing two or three Hereticks, and that warm her houſe too, may be avoided, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p n="66">66. They'll ſay it is a difficult thing to prove a Rogue perjur'd, and an Affidavit-man, and an Evidence ſhall find favour and Friends, 'tis hopefull, and if we ſwear (ſay they) to catch and trap a man out of his life and Eſtate, we are upon our Oaths, (ſo they are every hour of the day but when they ſleep, but no ſooner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, but the firſt is a prayer to God, damn me) none can contradict us, the Jury is bound to believe us whether they will or no, and in ſpight of their Heart and Conſcience (they muſt go according to their Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, yes, yes, the Juries well know their duty, well know you and your Evidence too) none know to the contrary, an Oath is an Oath, they go on and ſay before Death and the day of Judgment, wee'll Repent and get a Pardon from our Ghoſtly-Father; nay, perhaps they have one before hand in their Pockets, <hi>Jub Sigillo piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris, vel Sacerdotis.</hi> But your Ghoſtly-Father, nor their Father.—<hi>Pa—Pa pater patrum,</hi> cannot deliver the falſe Swearers and Men-catchers from the juſt Judgment and Diſcovery of the Father of Spirits, who proteſts he will be both Judg and Jury and Witneſs too againſt the falſe Swearers, Adulterers and Oppreſſors, <hi>Mil.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 19.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62653:13"/>
            <p n="67">67. There was a Plot, a horrid Plot and Conſpiracy by the Chief Prieſt and Scribes againſt our bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer's Life, and willing enough they were to kill him but they feared the people. Wherefore they Reſolved he ſhould ſuffer by the Law of the Land, for Treaſon, in preverting the Nation, and forbiding to give Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> &amp;c. But how ſhall they prove the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment? Why that's the eaſieſt thing in the World; it is but looking out (and they are always at hand) ſome Knights of the Poſt, ſome falſe Affidavit-men, catch-Poles, and falſe Evidence, and the Sham-plot is perfected, the Indictment prov'd, and the buſineſs done. Therefore all heads to work, eſpecially the Chief-prieſts (they muſt be in at a dead lift) and Elders and all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel ſought falſe witneſs againſt Jeſus to put him to death, but found none: Yea though many falſe witneſs came, yet they found none. That was hard, but at the laſt came two falſe witneſs. And theſe did the buſineſs, for which they came, for which they were hired, and they were <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Evidence, and ſwore for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and ſwore the matter home, and theſe catchers carried the cauſe againſt the greateſt Innocence. Mighty glad (no doubt) were the Chief-Prieſt, and Elders and Councel; and mightily careſſed and much made of were theſe two ſham Evidences and falſe witneſs that ſwore home; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially after the former falſe witneſs miſcarried in the Attempt, as not having got their leſſon ſufficiently by heart. They had needs be men of cunning and ability that can ſwear thorow-ſtich and cleaverly, mixing ſome Truth and probable Circumſtances amongſt many, and amongſt the main Lie: There is art in daubing. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 23.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62653:13"/>
            <p n="68">68. From a Lion, a Tiger, a Woolf or a Serpent, we may make ſome defence and proviſion, but this kind of Snake is <hi>Anguis in herba,</hi> no fore-ſight, no cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no prudence, no innocence can defend from the ſting of this forked, venomous, and murdering Tongue, except a man abandon all ſociety with Man-kind. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. p.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p n="69">69. Men may keep theſe Snakes (and but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps neither) out of their Bed-chamber, ſcarcely out of their Houſes, however not out of publick Houſes, Churches, Courts of Judicature, Exchanges, and publick Aſſemblies, ſo that if they can but bring good proof of the <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> as that they were at ſuch a time in ſuch a Church, Aſſembly, Exchange, publick meeting in Court, City, or Country; let them alone to ſwear what they heard there. Theſe (I ſay) are the great Plague, the non-ſuch Peſts of all Society, the common Nuſance: no former Age (that I read of) can parallel ours for improvement of Vice and Miſchief. What Blockheads were the <hi>French-mens</hi> Anceſtors in the Art of poyſoning, in compariſon of the preſent skill and dexterity? What Blockheads were the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the <hi>Native Iriſh</hi> in all Arts and Myſteries imaginable in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages? But now how ingenious (though ſome of them are but Bunglers ſtill, and enough to deſtroy a neat well-laid, and well-contriv'd Plot in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for want of skill in a <hi>ſubtile Intrigue</hi>) but time and good Tutors may improve them, if there be firſt a willing mind. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="70">70. The ſin of ſetting Snares to catch men is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon (too too common God knows) in theſe days; ſuch ſhamming, trepanning, that ſcarce any honeſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62653:14"/>man in <hi>England</hi> of any Eminency, but has or may have cauſe to ſay with holy <hi>David;—Every day they wreſt my words Ibid. p.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p n="71">71. Some think our Diviſions are ſo great, that they will not have a ſhorter period than the Wars and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Greece;</hi> of the end whereof the <hi>Oracle</hi> of <hi>Apollo</hi> (being conſulted) replyed,—They ſhall ſurceaſe when they ſhould double the Altar at <hi>Delphos;</hi> was Cubique form (which is impoſſible!) Yet I have other thoughts, more faith, and better hope that our Diſtractions will find a happy Concluſion, and the depth of Plots and Sham-plots in good time be fathom'd, ſounded to the bottom, and diſcovered; yet truly, I think (as is ſaid of the Altar at <hi>Delphos</hi>) a period and end of our Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions is impoſſible, till all <hi>Popiſh Altars, Popiſh hopes,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh claim</hi> (by the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Emiſſaries)</hi> to theſe Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Propagation of his Superſtition amongſt us, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate and rooted out, nay root and branch: for there always were Popiſh Plots in the Reigns of all our Kings, ever ſince the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> have been rejected, and whilſt there is a fair proſpect and hopes of Redemption of this <hi>Golden Fleece</hi> (though they be but Glimpſes) there will be <hi>Popiſh Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> except they Apoſtatize from the Principles of <hi>Popery. Ibid. p.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p n="72">72. Better a thouſand times (if poſſible) to die a true <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and a true <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> by the Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plots, falſe Witneſſes, and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Machinations, than willingly to enſlave a man's ſelf and Poſterity, Soul, Body, Honour, Honeſty, Religion, and Eſtate, to Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary and Popiſh ſway; I put them together: for like <hi>Hippocrates</hi>'s Twins) they are born, and live, and die together. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 34.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62653:14"/>
            <p n="73">73. 'Tis ſenceleſs to doubt the being of a <hi>Popiſh-Plot,</hi> that never ceas'd (ſince <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.) in <hi>England:</hi> But now by <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters it infallibly appears, that they never had ſuch bleſſed hopes of converting theſe Three Kingdoms ſince the Bon-fires in <hi>Smithfield</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, as now at this time, now that—</p>
            <p>And the more impudently they deny ſo clear a truth, the more cauſe we have to abominate the Villany of that Religion, that hardens men in Lies or Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions even to death; and the more they deny it, after ſuch apparent and manifold conviction, the more ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious and dangerous it is by the combined endeavours to conceal it, and to turn the edge thereof upon the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. Ibid. p.</hi> 35.</p>
            <p n="74">74. Indeed no man can deny but 'tis politickly and craftily done, to endeavour to put out the eyes of thoſe men that are moſt quick-ſighted to diſcern their dark myſterious and helliſh Intrigues: Or if they could but be <hi>Godfreydiz'd,</hi> ſtrangl'd, hang'd or ſtabb'd, the buſineſs would be done as effectually, and to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. Eſpecially, if the Sham-evidences would but be improv'd and manag'd with ſome Lawyer's Hackney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue, whoſe Conſcience is ſo often ſold <hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> right or wrong, for Plaintiff or Defendant (who bids moſt, and who comes firſt) proſtituted and ſet to ſale, when Merchandize is indifferently and equally madeof Truth and Falſhood) the Snare of catching men would be the ſtronger, and the Feat more currant. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 36.</p>
            <p n="75">75. A Chriſtian is bound to chooſe the Communion of the pureſt Church, and not to leave that for a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt one, though called never ſo Catholick. <hi>Silling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet's Idolatry of the Church of</hi> Rome. <hi>p.</hi> 8.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62653:15"/>
            <p n="76">76. Eccleſiaſtical Laws muſt be impoſed ſo as to leave our liberty unharmed. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Taylor<hi>'s Caſes of Conſcience.</hi> p. 301.</p>
            <p n="77">77. Laws of burden are alwaies againſt Charity. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 310.</p>
            <p n="78">78. Ceremonies oblige no longer than they miniſter to the end of Charity. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 314.</p>
            <p n="79">79. Eccleſiaſtical Laws muſt ever promote the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and the good of Souls, but muſt never put a Snare or Stumbling-block to Conſciences.—The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which the Lord hath given is for Edification, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 323.</p>
            <p n="80">80. Though ſignificant Ceremonies can be for Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the Church in ſome degree, and in ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; yet its to be conſidered, whether the introducing of ſuch things doth not deſtroy the Church, not only in her Chriſtian Liberty, but in the ſimplicity and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and ſpirituality of her Religion, by inſenſible changing it into Ceremonial and External Service. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid.</hi> 325.</p>
            <p n="81">81. A Symbolical Right of Humane Invention, to ſignifie what it doth not effect, and then introduced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſolemn Service of God; is ſo like the vain Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations and repreſentations forbidden in the ſecond Commandment, that the very ſuſpicion is more againſt Edification, than their uſe can pretend to. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="82">82. Were we ſo happy but to take off things grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unceſſary by all, and ſuſpected by many, and judged
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62653:15"/>unlawful by ſome, and to make nothing the bounds of our communion, but what Chriſt hath done; <hi>viz.</hi> One Faith, one Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> allowing a liberty for Matters of Indifferency, and bearing with the weakneſs of thoſe who cannot bear things which others account lawful, we might indeed be reſtored to a true Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Luſtre far ſooner than by furbuſhing up ſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquated Ceremonies, which can derive their Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree no higher than from ſome ancient Cuſtom and Tradition. God will one day convince men, that the Union of the Church lies more in the Unity of Faith and Affection, than in Uniformity of doubtful Rites and Ceremonies. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s <hi>Irenic. p.</hi> 121.</p>
            <p n="83">83. It would be ſtrange the Church ſhould require more than Chriſt himſelf did, and make other Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of her Communion, than our Saviour did of Diſcipleſhip, <hi>&amp;c. Preface to Irenic. p.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="84">84. Without all Controverſie, the main In-let of all the Diſtractions, Confuſions, and Diviſions of the Chriſtian World, hath been by adding other Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Church-Communion than Chriſt hath done. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="85">85. And therefore were there that Spirit of mutual Condeſcention which was moſt certainly in <hi>Eccleſia pr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo primitiva,</hi> in the firſt and truly Primitive Church in the Apoſtles times, our breaches as to this thing too might ſoon be cloſed up, and the <hi>Voice of Schiſm</hi> be heard amongſt us no more. <hi>Irenic. p.</hi> 122.</p>
            <p n="86">86. What Charter hath Chriſt given the Church to bind men up to, more than himſelf hath done, or to exclude thoſe from her Society who may be admitted into Heaven? <hi>Ibid p.</hi> 8.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62653:16"/>
            <p n="87">87. It cannot but be looked upon as a Token o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God's ſevere diſpleaſure againſt us, if any though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Propoſals of Peace between us and the <hi>Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> ſhould meet with ſuch entertainment among many; and yet any faint offers of Union and Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation among our ſelves, be ſo coldly embraced and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 123.</p>
            <p n="88">88. The leaſt Peg ſcrued up too high in the Church, ſoon cauſeth a great deal of diſcord, and quickly puts mens Spirits out of tune. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 47.</p>
            <p n="89">89. Nothing ſhould be impoſed as neceſſary but what is clearly revealed in the Word of God. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 62.</p>
            <p n="90">90. But as for the way, manner, and circumſtances of Worſhip, we are to follow the poſitive Laws of God. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 36.</p>
            <p n="91">91. Certainly the Primitive Church that did not charge mens faith with ſuch a load of Articles, as now in theſe latter Ages men are charged with, would much leſs burthen men with impoſing doubtful Practiſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as the ground of Church-communion. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 122.</p>
            <p n="92">92. Let men turn and wind themſelves which way they will, by the very ſame Arguments that any will prove Separation from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> lawful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe required unlawful things, as the Conditions of her Communion, it will be proved lawful not to conform to any ſuſpected or unlawful practice required by any Church-government upon the ſame terms, if the thing ſo required, be after ſerious and ſober enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, judged unwarrantable by a man's own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62653:16"/>And withal its to be conſidered, that our beſt Writers lay the Imputation of <hi>Schiſm</hi> not on thoſe who withdraw Communion, but on them for requiring ſuch Conditions of Communion (whereby they did rather eject men out of their Communion, than others ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from them.) <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 120, 121.</p>
            <p n="93">93. The Epiſcopal men will hardly find any evidence in Scripture, or the practice of the Apoſtles, for Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches conſiſting of many fixed Congregations for Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, under the charge of one Perſon, <hi>&amp;c. Ibid. pag.</hi> 114, 115.</p>
            <p n="94">94. From this monopolizing of Churches to Parties, hath proceeded that ſtrange uncharitableneſs towards all who come not up to every circumſtance of their way and method. <hi>Preface to Irenic. p.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="95">95. Princes have no right to call or confirm Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but to preſerve ſuch as be ſent of God, and give them liberty for their preaching, and ſecurity for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and if Princes refuſe ſo to do, God's Labourers muſt go forward with that which is commanded them from Heaven. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bilſon <hi>of Subjection, p.</hi> 236.</p>
            <p n="96">96, When we ſhall come to the Queſtion of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> I perſwade my ſelf, that I ſhall plainly ſhew, that the moſt vehement Accuſers are the greateſt Offenders; and that they are indeed at this time the greateſt <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks,</hi> who make the way to Salvation narrower, the Yoak of Chriſt heavier, the difference of Faith grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Conditions of Eccleſiaſtical Government har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſtraiter, then they were made at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by Chriſt and his Apoſtles: they who talk of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but aim at Tyranny, and will have peace with none but with their Slaves and Vaſſals. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s <hi>Safe way. p.</hi> 180.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62653:17"/>
            <p n="97">97. Becauſe the uſe of Sacraments in a Chriſtian Church ought to be the moſt free from all exception, and they ought to be ſo adminiſtred as rather to invite than diſcourage ſcrupulous perſons from joyning in them: I do think it would be a part of Chriſtian wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and condeſcention in the Governours of our Church to remove thoſe Bars from a full Communion. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation. p.</hi> 82.</p>
            <p n="98">98. <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> as they are in common uſe, are two Theological Scare-crows, which they who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a Party in Religion, uſe to fright away ſuch, as making an Inquiry into it, are ready to relinquiſh and oppoſe it, if it appear either erroneous or ſuſpicious. <hi>Hales</hi>'s <hi>Tract of Schiſm. p.</hi> 191.</p>
            <p n="99">99. In regard of divers Diſtempers men are ſubject to, Diſſention and Diſunion are often neceſſary, when either falſe or uncertain Concluſions are obtruded for Truth, and acts either unlawful or miniſtring juſt ſcruple, are required of us to be perform'd; in theſe Caſes, Conſent is Conſpiracy, and open Contention is not Faction or Schiſm, but due Chriſtian Animoſity. <hi>Tract of Schiſm. p.</hi> 194.</p>
            <p n="100">100. Where cauſe of Schiſm is neceſſary, there 'tis not he that ſeparates, but he that occaſions the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is the Schiſmatick. <hi>p.</hi> 199.</p>
            <p n="101">101. In all publick Meetings pretending Holineſs, ſo there be nothing done, but what true Devotion and Piety brook, why may I not be preſent in them and uſe communion with them? <hi>p.</hi> 29.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62653:17"/>
            <p n="102">102. Were <hi>Liturgies</hi> and <hi>Publick Forms</hi> of <hi>Service</hi> ſo framed, as that they admitted not of particular and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Fancies, but contained only ſuch things in which all Chriſtians do agree, <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Opinion</hi> were utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vaniſhed, For conſider of all the <hi>Liturgies</hi> that are or ever have been, and remove from them whatſoever is ſcandalous to any Party, and leave nothing but what all agree on, and the event ſhall be, that the <hi>Publick Service of God</hi> ſhall no ways ſuffer: Whereas to load our <hi>Publick Forms</hi> with <hi>private Fancies,</hi> upon which we differ, is the moſt Soveraign way to perpetuate <hi>Schiſm</hi> unto the worlds end. <hi>Prayer, Confeſſion, Thanskgiving, Reading the Scripture, Adminiſtration of Sacraments,</hi> in the plaineſt manner, were matter enough to furniſh out a ſufficient <hi>Liturgy,</hi> though nothing either of <hi>private Opinion,</hi> or of <hi>Church Pomp,</hi> of <hi>Garments,</hi> of <hi>preſcribed Geſtures,</hi> of <hi>Imagery,</hi> of <hi>Muſick,</hi> of <hi>matter concerning the Dead,</hi> of many <hi>Superfluities,</hi> which creep into the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, under the name of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſelf: For to charge <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Liturgies</hi> with things unneceſſary, was the firſt beginning of all Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and when Scruples of Conſcience began to be made or pretended, then <hi>Schiſm</hi> began to break in. <hi>Page</hi> 216, 217.</p>
            <p n="103">103. If the <hi>Spiritual Guides</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> would be a little ſparing of incumbring <hi>Churches</hi> with <hi>Superfluities,</hi> and not over rigid either in reviving obſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> or impoſing new, there were far leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Schiſm</hi> or <hi>Superstition</hi> and all the Inconvenience were likely to enſue, would be but this, they ſhould in ſo doing, yield a little to the Imbecillities of Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; a thing which St. <hi>Paul</hi> would never have refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to do. <hi>p.</hi> 218.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62653:18"/>
            <p n="104">104. Whereſoever falſe or ſuſpected Opinions are made a piece of the <hi>Church Liturgy,</hi> he that ſeparates is not the <hi>Schiſmatick;</hi> for it is a like unlawfull to make Profeſſion of known or ſuſpected falſhoods, as to put in practice unlawful or ſuſpected Actions. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="105">105. They but abuſe themſelves and others, that would perſwade us, that Biſhops by Chriſt's Inſtitution have any Superiority over men further than of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; or that any Biſhop is Superiour to another. <hi>Page</hi> 224.</p>
            <p n="106">106. It hath been the common diſeaſe of Chriſtians from the beginning, not to content themſelves with that meaſure of Faith, which God and Scripture have afforded us; but out of a vain deſire to know more than is revealed, and have attempted to diſcuſs things of which we have no light from Reaſon nor Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Neither have they reſted here, but upon pretence of <hi>Church Authority,</hi> which is none, or Tradition, which for the moſt part is but figment; they have perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily concluded, and confidently impoſed upon others. <hi>p.</hi> 212, 213.</p>
            <p n="107">107. In <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> there is neither high nor low; and in giving Honour every man ſhould be ready to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer another before himſelf: which ſayings cut off all Claim to Superiority by Title of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> except men can think theſe things were ſpoken only to poor and private men. <hi>p.</hi> 125.</p>
            <p n="108">108. This abuſe of Chriſtianity, to make it lacquey to Ambition is a vice for which I have no extraordinary name of Ignominy, and an ordinary I will not give it, leaſt you ſhould take ſo tranſcendent a vice to be but Trivial. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62653:18"/>
            <p n="109">109. All pious Aſſemblies in times of Perſecution and Corruption, howſoever Practiſed, are indeed or rather alone the lawfull Congregations; and publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, though according to Law, are nothing elſe but Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots and Conventicles, if ſtained with Corruption, and perſtition. <hi>P</hi> 231.</p>
            <p n="110">110. The Church as it imports a viſible Company in Earth, is nothing elſe but the Company of Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, whereſoever Diſperſt in the Earth. To Define it by Monarchy, under one viſible head, is of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty crept up, ſince men began to change the Spirituall Kingdom of Chriſt to ſecular Pride and Tyranny, and a thing never heard of, either in the Scriptures, or in the writings of the Ancients. <hi>p.</hi> 137.</p>
            <p n="111">111. Schiſm is ſometimes upon the account of matter of Fact, as when it is through error taken for neceſſary, that an <hi>Eaſter</hi> muſt be kept; and upon worſe then Error if I may ſo ſpeak, (for it was no leſs then a point of <hi>Judaiſm forced upon the Church</hi>) p. 202.</p>
            <p n="112">112. It is Schiſm upon wilfulneſs that brings Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with it, Schiſm upon miſtake, and Schiſm upon juſt occaſion, hath in it ſelf little hurt, if any at all. <hi>p.</hi> 84.</p>
            <p n="113">113. Why ſhould it be any longer ſaid, and that with ſo much colour of Truth, that Loyalty and Piety can not dwell together in the ſame Breaſt? Why ſhould it be any longer ſaid to our ſhame, that ſwearing, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and deriding Religion, and making a mock of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, are the principall Badges of ſuch as call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Loyaliſts? <hi>Ellis</hi>'s Sermon before the Marquiſs of <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi> p. 38.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62653:19"/>
            <p n="114">114. A Citizens Skull is but a thing to try the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of a Soldiers Sword upon. <hi>Leſtrang</hi>'s Apology. <hi>p.</hi> 48.</p>
            <p n="115">115. The very mention of a Parliament Inrages them, and there is reaſon for it, there heads are forfeited, and if Law lives, they muſt periſh: But all this while, are not we in a good Condition, when the Tranſgreſſors of the Law, muſt be the Judges of it. <hi>Apology. p.</hi> 51.</p>
            <p n="116">116. A Furious Busſle the Presbyterians make with ſilly people for fear of Popery. <hi>Leſtrange</hi>'s Relapſed <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate. p.</hi> 240.</p>
            <p n="117">117. I Defie any man to produce another Gentleman in the Kings Dominions under my Circumſtances, that hath ſuffered ſo many illegall, Arbitrary and mean In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtices from any abuſers of the Kings Bounty, inſomuch that after one and thirty years faithful ſervice to the Crown, the Bread hath been taken out of my Mouth, and in a large proportion ſhared among ſome of thoſe very people that purſued the late King to the Block; <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrange's</hi> Engliſhmans Birth Right. <hi>p.</hi> 44.</p>
            <p n="118">118. Who knows not that Intereſt governs the world, and that for Reaſons beſt known to themſelves, he that is a Proteſtant in his heart, may be induced rather to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear a Papiſt; and the other, though in Heart a Papiſt, may find it his Intereſt yet to ſeem a Proteſtant. <hi>Leſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g's</hi> further Diſcovery. <hi>p.</hi> 18,</p>
            <p n="119">119. We find the Court dangerouſly Thronged with Paraſities, Knaves Repreſented to the King for honeſt men, and honeſt men for Knaves. <hi>Leſtrange</hi>'s <hi>Caveat</hi> for Cavalliers, <hi>p.</hi> 12.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62653:19"/>
            <p n="120">120. If men will be Damn'd, they had better Damn Rich than Poor, and keep their Lacquies and their Whores, and at laſt go to Hell in Triumph. <hi>Le Strang</hi>'s Apology. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p n="121">121. A Pariſian Maſſacre, a Guiſian League, a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Treaſon, a Covenant Reformation, a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition Houſe, and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> High Court of Juſtice, the fighting for Reformation and bidding Defiance to Heaven by whom Kings Reign; theſe are Abominations ſo ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and Antichriſtian, as do <hi>non-plus</hi> Hyperbolies, and ſilence Invention; and next to theſe there is ſcarce any thing more. Criminal than the equally ſinful and Ridiculous Bill againſt the Succeſſion of his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Goulds</hi> Sermon, <hi>p.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p n="122">122. I believe the Framers of that Bill had a further Deſign than the Dukes Perſon, and am clearly of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that there is both a Popiſh Plot, and a Presbyterian one at this time againſt the Church or the King, or both in Conjunction. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="123">123. He that maintains ſuch a thing in a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Seſſion (ſpeaking of the Dukes Bill) is not ſo well qualified for <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> as <hi>Bedlam: Ibid p.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p n="123">123. The Doctrine of taking away the right of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion came from <hi>Rome,</hi> the People had it from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil <hi>&amp;c. Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="124">124. I bleſs God I have the Spirit of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man and uy knoes, due to God and the King, ſhall never be yielded up to Uſurpers, come what will, come Hanging, Burning, or any other, or all the Torments that exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Patience of the Primitive Chriſtians. <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 28.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62653:20"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Query. </seg>
               </label> Query. <hi>Whether this Blade be not more fool-hardy than valiant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="125">125. Infinite Obligations lieth on us to the greateſt thankfulneſs to our good God, for reſcuing theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from under the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke; and for theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of Mercy which he hath wrought for us, in blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many of their deep-laid Deſigns, their late great Conſpiracy, and late Sham-Plots, for the reducing us to our old Captivity. <hi>Dr.</hi> Fowler<hi>'s Sermon,</hi> p. 25.</p>
            <p n="126">126. He hath no participation of the God-like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Life, which is of a quarrelſom, contentious, uncharitable ſpirit. <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 27.</p>
            <p n="127">127. There are too too many among our ſelves, that do little conſult our Churches Intereſt, nor conſequently the Intereſt of the Proteſtant Religion, but greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve both, by their intemperate Heats, and branding all with the names of <hi>Fanaticks</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who are not come up to their Pitch, and in all things juſt of their Complexion; although they be as obedient to both their Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Superiors as themſelves. <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 28.</p>
            <p n="128">128. We ought by Love and Sweetneſs to encourage Men all we can, and not by Sowreneſs and Cenſoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs tempt thoſe to depart from us, who would gladly hold communion with us. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="129">129. Where we find an inclination towards return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any that have departed from us, we ſhould be glad to meet them half way, in order to the bringing them over to us. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="130">130. I do believe if all the Church of <hi>England</hi> were of this mind, it would greatly leſſen the number of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="131">131. There are too too many Debauchees in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who would be thought great Champions for the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62653:20"/>King and the Church, but do infinite prejudice to both, by mad and frantick expreſſions of their Zeal; and mighty honour to <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> by charging all with it, that run not with them to the ſame exceſs of Riot. <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 29.</p>
            <p n="132">132. One would think that theſe, whatſoever they pretend, do really deſign nothing more, than to make both the King and the Church as friendleſs as they are able; Heaven help them both, ſhould they ever be ſo unfortunate (which God forbid) as to ſtand in need of this ſort of People. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="133">133. Indeed if Huffing and Healthing, Curſing and Damning, and giving vile Names would do the buſineſs, then let them alone to protect the King and the Church; but former experience hath aſſured us, that thoſe are the beſt Weapons that moſt of them can boaſt of their being good at. A Neighbouring King, and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> may wiſh God's Bleſſing on the hearts of theſe Gentlemen; but our own King (whom God preſerve) and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> have little reaſon to con them thanks, for any ſervice they are like to do them. <hi>Ib.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Query. </seg>
               </label> Query. <hi>Whether</hi> Heraclitus, <hi>the</hi> Obſervator, <hi>and</hi> Thompſon, <hi>are then like to do the Church of</hi> England <hi>ſo much ſervice as they pretend to? And to ſhew that they act contrary to the King's mind, I ſhall conclude with two paſſages of His Majeſties Proclamation againſt Vicious and Debauched People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>We think it high time to ſhew Our diſlike of thoſe againſt whom We have been ever enough offended, though We could not in this manner declare it, who, under pretence of Affection to Us, and Our Service, aſſume to themſelves the liberty of Reviling, Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Reproaching others; and, as much as in them lies,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62653:21"/>endeavor to ſtifle and divert their good Inclinations to Our Service; and ſo to prevent that Reconciliation and Union of Hearts and Affections, which can onely, with God's Bleſſing, make Us rejoice in each other, and keep Our Enemies from rejoicing.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>There are likewiſe another ſort of Men, of whom We have heard much, and are ſufficiently aſhamed, who ſpend their time in Taverns, Tipling Houſes, and Debauchos, giving no other evidence of their Affection to Us, but in drinking Our Health, and inveighing againſt all others, who are not of their own diſſolute Temper; and who, in truth, have more diſcreited Our Cauſe, by the Licence of their Manners and Lives, than they could over advance it by their Affection or Courage.</q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>☞ There is lately Publiſhed an ingenious Piece, Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Horrid Sin of MAN-CATCHING.</hi> The Second Part: Or, further Diſcoveries and Arguments to prove, <hi>That there is no Proteſtant Plot:</hi> And that the Deſign of caſting a Plot upon them by the Suborned <hi>Man-catchers,</hi> was antecedent to the firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the <hi>Popiſh Plot.</hi> Together with ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſcoveries concerning Mr. <hi>Booth.</hi> Humbly Dedicated to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesbury.</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Jones,</hi> and are to be ſold by moſt Bookſellers. <hi>Price Six-pence.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
